<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.10.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-09-09T11:19:58-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Jack</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">Working Hard</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/09/08/working-hard.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Working Hard" /><published>2025-09-08T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-09-08T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/09/08/working-hard</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/09/08/working-hard.html"><![CDATA[<p>I spent a week this summer hiking a <a href="https://www.wta.org/go-hiking/hikes/pacific-crest-trail-section-j-snoqualmie-pass-to-stevens-pass-east">75 mile stretch of the PCT</a> with a friend. We averaged ~18 miles a day, and would typically hike for 12 hours, get into camp around 7 at night, and fall into our sleeping bags shortly thereafter. On some nights I would’ve loved to have a bit more time to recover, but there simply wasn’t another way to cover that kind of mileage without long hours.</p>

<p>So when I see posts <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/silicon-valley-china-996-work-schedule/">espousing constant availability like a 9-9-6 culture</a>, I kinda get it. More hours ~= more work done. No, I wasn’t walking as fast in the 12th hour as I was in the 5th- but I wasn’t being negatively productive; I was still putting one foot in front of the other. And there are absolutely some businesses in hypergrowth where that extra marginal foot matters.</p>

<p><a href="https://x.com/garrytan/status/1965124089875685532">Investors</a> and founders encouraging the phenomenon are also acting logically. VC investing is a <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/whaling-venture-capital-long-tale-long-tail-returns-nathan-sieminski-u9aic/">long-tail market where most companies will go to zero but the ones that make it are huge</a>. If investors can convince every employee at each of their portfolio companies to work an extra hour, they will see massive benefits. Founders are similar, but more highly concentrated into a single company. And even if their company fails, showing hustle to the right investors gives them a great chance of getting referred to a plum job.</p>

<p>All that to say: I get why the <a href="https://ramp.com/velocity/san-francisco-tech-workers-996-schedule?utm_source=twitter">9-9-6 culture has gained steam</a>. And even from the employees’ perspective it can make sense! Early employees won’t have founder-level equity<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, but they’ll have enough to be meaningful in the event of an exit. And many people find meaning and friendship at work- particularly if you just moved across the country to a west-coast city that’s thousands of miles away from everyone you’ve ever known.</p>

<p>But for the 99% of companies that aren’t truly in a hypergrowth phase, such a culture raises the floor but also lowers the ceiling. Why?</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>It discourages creativity.</strong> Most people can only do a <a href="https://www.oliverburkeman.com/fourhours">handful of hours of creative work a day</a>. If your business isn’t in hypergrowth (but is trying to get there), your limiter is likely more creative ideas rather than more execution time. Spending those extra hours on pure execution rather than encouraging boredom will <a href="https://journals.aom.org/doi/10.5465/amd.2017.0033">stifle your creativity</a>.
    <ul>
      <li>As an example, I’ve worked with some incredibly talented colleagues who never learned how to scale themselves. As they accumulated more responsibilities they just worked more hours. At a certain point they physically couldn’t work more and they couldn’t keep pace with the organization. Working fewer hours would’ve forced them to develop effective systems to delegate and check in.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>It risks burning out the team</strong>. Even if you’re somehow ok with churning 90% of the team every few years, <a href="https://x.com/danluu/status/1477358578792951808">losing your 10% of top performers can take years to recover from</a>.</li>
  <li><strong>It stops you from sprinting when it matters.</strong> If everyone is already going all out, you don’t have that extra gear to push for the big compliance deadline or upcoming customer demo. If I had seen a bear in my 12th hour of hiking I wasn’t going to be able to run away no matter how much I wanted to.</li>
</ul>

<p>Beyond the business case, I also just think it’s wrong at a personal level. Meeting your partner or life-long friends is often the most valuable thing you can get out of your 20s and 30s, but <a href="https://www.smithsonianmag.com/arts-culture/new-insights-how-american-couples-meet-180973335/">most people don’t meet them at work</a>. Instead, I think for some people work can almost be a retreat to something that they know and are good at, rather than a scary arena with unknown rules. But you don’t get better at making friends or dating by avoiding it.</p>

<p>Rather than building a team of people who constantly work long hours, I’d rather build a team of people that deeply care. The truth is, most of these people <em>will</em> work longer hours than normal. But they’re intentionally choosing how and when to work, and have shaped their routines accordingly. Maybe they’re logging off to go for a run every afternoon but still thinking about work in the shower. Or maybe they’re leaving early to see their kids’ soccer practice every Monday and checking Slack when they get back. They work hard because they care about it and get value out of it, not because they’re performing to an arbitrary standard<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. Those are the kind of people I want to work with.</p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>This assumes the company exits in a standard way. With some of the acqui-hire deal structures the valley is using now where payouts for early employees are not guaranteed, this starts to look downright predatory. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>A common excuse is that measuring how much someone cares is <strong>much</strong> more difficult than tracking hours spent in the office, which is ~trivial. But just because it’s the easy answer doesn’t mean it’s the right one. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I spent a week this summer hiking a 75 mile stretch of the PCT with a friend. We averaged ~18 miles a day, and would typically hike for 12 hours, get into camp around 7 at night, and fall into our sleeping bags shortly thereafter. On some nights I would’ve loved to have a bit more time to recover, but there simply wasn’t another way to cover that kind of mileage without long hours.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Losing (and Maintaining) Trust in Your Company</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/09/03/losing-trust-in-company.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Losing (and Maintaining) Trust in Your Company" /><published>2025-09-03T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-09-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/09/03/losing-trust-in-company</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/09/03/losing-trust-in-company.html"><![CDATA[<p>At any given time most people have a laundry-list of frustrations with their job. Yet even in the face of major disappointments like getting passed over for a promotion, they will often still feel positive about their work overall. Maybe they still really like their coworkers, or believe in the mission, or just enjoy the day-to-day mundanity enough that they’re ok with some frustration in the bigger picture.</p>

<p>But this can also quickly flip into a negative spiral, where every interaction suddenly becomes a major issue and sends them into the red. Some signs you might be experiencing this spiral include:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Your blood pressure spikes every time a certain person slacks you.</li>
  <li>You feeling like every decision getting made is wrong.</li>
  <li>You get irritated every time a specific initiative is raised.</li>
</ul>

<p>Often in tech this behavior is referenced to as “burnout”, where you detach from work due to feeling exhausted from a prolonged period of stress. But I don’t think that’s quite the right metaphor. Burnout leads to a passive detachment, not an active irritation like a spiral. Instead I’d liken this feeling to something closer to <a href="https://www.gottman.com/blog/blame-resentment-and-negative-sentiment-override/">a negative sentiment override</a>. The subtleties here matter because if you misdiagnose your feeling as burnout, your instinct may be to step away and rest. But getting out of a negative spiral requires active effort, not just time off.</p>

<p>Instead, I find the <a href="https://sketchplanations.com/the-trust-battery">trust battery</a> a much more helpful metaphor to think about this, as a battery that exists between you and your company. Positive actions like a raise or liking your team can raise the battery level to such a point that even large negatives like disagreeing with the company strategy or being overworked for months can still leave you generally positive about the experience. But if you deplete the battery for too long without any corresponding boosts, you’ll end up in the negative spiral and either be miserable or leave your job.</p>

<p>Successfully completing a few large projects each year or getting a regular raise will often leave you at a high enough stasis point. But just like gamblers going broke after hours at a table, if you stay long enough at one job, probability alone means that at some point the negatives will outweigh the positives. This is especially true if you’re at a job for a long (4+ year) stint like I was at <a href="https://www.angellist.com/">AngelList</a>.</p>

<p>I also found that these “easy” positive events weren’t always fully in my control. Getting a raise might depend on the company’s financials, how my manager viewed compensation, etc. In an ideal world my company would also do their part to keep me engaged, and I certainly view it as one of my primary duties as a manager. But even great managers are going to fuck up, and I don’t want to be relying on any outside force. At the end of the day it’s my life, and I need to take <a href="https://conscious.is/video/are-you-taking-100-responsibility">100% responsibility</a> for it.</p>

<p>So I developed a few habits to more actively keep myself engaged:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Regularly interviewing candidates</strong>. Any interviewer knows that one of the most frequent questions you’re asked is “what do you like best about the company?” I found that coming up with an authentic answer and regularly repeating it to yourself and others almost indoctrinates you to believe it, just like <a href="https://www.bps.org.uk/research-digest/adopting-smile-can-make-you-feel-happier-large-global-study-finds">smiling can make you happier</a>.</li>
  <li><strong>Carving out time for energy boosting activities</strong>. Especially as a manager, often times your wins come from long term efforts like coaching your report and seeing them take over and lead a meeting flawlessly or shipping a quarter long roadmap. But if I’m having a bad day, I know that taking on a small ticket in the backlog and seeing all the tests go green will give me an energy boost right when I need it. I really like the term “<a href="https://www.intercom.com/blog/first-rule-prioritization-no-snacking/">snacking</a>” for this work. Like junk-food, I have to be careful not to over-indulge this impulse since it’s very rarely the most valuable work I could be doing. But I do think it’s valuable work when it lets me manage my mental health.</li>
  <li><strong>Fixing things yourself</strong>. Often decisions may seem out of your control, especially as you go farther down the org chart. But a reasonable percentage of the time you actually will be able to drive change simply by being the person in the company who cares the most about it. Even if you ultimately aren’t successful or things truly are out of your control, you will certainly be remembered by leadership as someone who cares. Whereas if you don’t even try, you never had a chance.</li>
  <li><strong>Actively building relationships outside my organization who are above me in the org chart</strong>. These diagonal relationships helped me trust the intent behind every decision, because I knew that the people making the call had good reasons— even if I didn’t agree.</li>
  <li>As a final test, <strong>taking a recruiter call or first interview externally</strong> can be very revealing. After the call, do you feel excited or nervous? Are there initiatives you’ll miss seeing to fruition? People you want to see grow a bit more? Taking that first step towards leaving can remind you what you value about your current company, or confirm it’s time to move on. Either way, you get some much needed clarity.</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[At any given time most people have a laundry-list of frustrations with their job. Yet even in the face of major disappointments like getting passed over for a promotion, they will often still feel positive about their work overall. Maybe they still really like their coworkers, or believe in the mission, or just enjoy the day-to-day mundanity enough that they’re ok with some frustration in the bigger picture.]]></summary></entry></feed>